<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Queenes Maiestie at Hampton Courte, the 19. of February laste paste. By VVilliam Iames Doctour of Diuinitie</title>
            <author>James, William, 1542-1617.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1578</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 65 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04351</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14465</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107697</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8123</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04351)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8123)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 555:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Queenes Maiestie at Hampton Courte, the 19. of February laste paste. By VVilliam Iames Doctour of Diuinitie</title>
                  <author>James, William, 1542-1617.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Henry Bynneman,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno Domini. 1578. Aprilis, 24.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  16th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:2"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the Queenes Maieſtie at Hampton Courte, the 19. <hi>of February laſte paſte. By</hi> VVilliam Iames <hi>Doctour of Diuinitie.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Henry Bynneman</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>¶ Imprinted at London by Henry Bynneman. <hi>Anno Domini.</hi> 1578. <hi>Aprilis,</hi> 24.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:3"/>
            <head>A Sermon preached at Hampton Court.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezrae.</hi> 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT the aduerſaries of Iudah and Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, hearde that the children of the cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuity builded the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple vnto the lorde God of Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2 And they came to Zerub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel, and to the chiefe fathers, &amp; ſaid vnto them, we wil builde with you, for we ſeeke the Lorde your God, as ye do, and we haue ſacrificed vnto him ſince the time of Eſar Haddon king of Aſſhur which brought vs vp hither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3 Then Zerubbabel and Ieſua and the reſt of the chiefe fathers of Iſrael, ſaide vnto them, it is not for you, but for vs, to builde the houſe vnto our God, for we our
<pb facs="tcp:8123:4"/>ſelues togither vvil builde to the Lorde God of Iſrael as king Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus the king of Perſia hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Od that firſt created man to his owne image, and placed him as Lorde of Paradiſe, that after his fall recomforted him, that the ſéede of the woman ſhould bruſe the Serpentes head, that with moſt grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous promiſes bleſſed Abraham and his poſteritie, that ledde his people through the wilderneſſe by the hande of Moyſes and Aaron, that ſente them faythfull Iudges and zealous Prieſts, to execute iuſtice and maintayne truthe, that after long contempt of his mercyfull call (by many of his Prophets) gaue them ouer to be ſchooled by the king of Babilon, that ſuffered their temple to bee raced, and themſelues moſte miſerably to be entreated: that God that at no tyme can forget his faithfull people, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membreth
<pb facs="tcp:8123:4"/>them when they are in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and reſcueth them in the perillous tyme, bycauſe he will not ſuffer <hi>Virgam peccatorum ſuper ſortem iuſtorum:</hi> Pſal. <hi>100</hi> at once worketh thrée ſtrange wonders.</p>
            <p>Fyrſt he inflameth King Cyrus with an earneſt deſire, not only to dimiſſe the people helde in captiuitie, but alſo to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore vnto them all ſuche veſſells &amp; trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures as Nabuchadnezer hadde before taken out of the Temple.</p>
            <p>Secondly, he rayſeth vp thrée notable guydes, thrée excellent and rare men, for the preſeruation of hys people nowe after their returne from babylon, Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabell, Ezra, and Nehemias.</p>
            <p>Thyrdly, he encourageth the people with all earneſtneſſe to trauaile in the worke of the houſe of God, ſo that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the wearineſſe of the captiuitie whiche they had endured, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> true ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God of a long ſeaſon vnfrequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, nor the pleaſures whiche Babylon offered, coulde once wythdrawe theſe weake and féebled perſons.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:5"/>
            <p>The ſumme is, the ſnare is broken, Iſraell is deliuered, Zorobabel, Ezra, Nehemias, the people al apply their bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe, deſiring in hearte no one thyng ſo muche, as to erect the Temple of the Lorde to adua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce the glory of their deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed God. But ſée, the aduerſaries of Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah &amp; Beniamin came not of any co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, but craftily to ſuppla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t theſe work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. It ſo falleth out, that if God haue a Church, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Diuel, if he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not hinder it, yet wil looke to haue an oare in it: if Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes worke wonders, Pharaos ſootheſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers will vſe an apiſhe imitation. The Apoſtles, Peter, Paule, Barnabas, ſhal no ſooner teſtifye the trueth of Ieſus Chriſt, than Simon and Elymas the ſorcerers wil be at ynches to peruerte the ryght wayes of the Lorde. If Paul preache at Athens, or at Epheſus, then ſhall he ſurely finde either Stoikes, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picures, or Iewes, or ſome ſecte of miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creants ready to miſſe-leade Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple. The enuious ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that when the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants ſléepe ſoweth tares to choake the wheat, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> plucketh the word of God out
<pb facs="tcp:8123:5"/>of the harts of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> hearers <hi>ne crederent &amp; ſeruarentur,</hi> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſomtime like a roaryng Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſéeketh who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may deuoure, and at another time, can turn himſelfe into an Angel of light, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo ſhook y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> conſciences of Caine &amp; Iudas, that they thought their ſins greater than coulde be forgiuen, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſo cunningly bleared Saules eies with the counterfaite ſhape of Samuel, and made Ananias and his wife to lye to the holye Ghoſte. That man of ſinne, as a Spirite ſawe the intente of Iſraell, and as an enimy by all poſſible meanes go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to hinder the building of the houſe of God. The diuel and y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Samaritans ſaw, that ſo long as Kyng Cyrus fauoured the Iewes, and the reedifying of the Temple, that ſo lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g it was vnpoſſible openly to hurt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or hinder it: and therefore nowe after that frowning wyll not ſerue, he vſeth a far more cunning ſhifte, he beginneth now to flatter and ſpeake faire. You haue a long time endured trouble, your treaſure is waſted, your bodies weakned, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> work is heauy, your ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth is féeble, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> charge
<pb facs="tcp:8123:6"/>greate, your ſubſtance ſmall: we Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabell, and you the reſte of the chiefe of Iſrael, we wil ioyne with you in this worke: diſtruſte vs not, for wee ſéeke the Lord your God, as you do, and we haue ſacrificed vnto hym ſince the tyme of Eſar Haddon, whyche brought vs vppe hither. Whome might not theſe ſugred ſpeaches haue deceyued? we will builde, we ſéeke the Lorde with you, wee ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to him as you do. But that God that euen in that ſame houre inſtructeth his what to anſwere, and that hathe lefte to hys ſeruantes iudgement to diſcerne the ſprytes whether they be of God or no, here in a trice, teacheth Zorobabell, Ioſua, and the reſt of the Elders to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweare: <hi>It is not for you and vs to builde togither.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will not ſtande heere to diſcuſſe why thys Booke, and the nexte of Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias are accompted Canonical, neither why the other of Eſdras are refuſed. I purpoſe onelye at thys tyme briefly to reſte on theſe two pointes: the aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
<pb facs="tcp:8123:6"/>comming: and Zorobabel, Ieſhua, and the reſt of Iſraelles reiecting of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Of theſe that I may ſo ſpeake as maye redounde to gods glory, I moſt humbly craue your Chriſtian ayde in earneſte prayer.</p>
            <p>Theſe Iewes nowe returned from ſeauentie yeares captiuitie, and nowe in hand with reedifying the houſe of God, and deſirous euery man to abide by his tackling, at y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> firſt are ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wyth theſe ſuttle Samaritanes: <hi>Let vs build with you:</hi> this they ſayd, intending nothyng more than indéede to pull downe. They ſawe thus much with Scribes &amp; Phaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies, that as if new Chriſt were ſuffered to grow vp, that then al the people wold go after hym: and that if Paul myghte be allowed to preache at Epheſus, that then Diana ſhould haue a great downe fall: ſo if the buylding of the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple might go forwarde, that then the Idols of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria would be but little ſet by.</p>
            <p>There are in theſe ſuperſtitious I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolaters two things worth the conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration:
<pb facs="tcp:8123:7"/>their conſent &amp; agréement vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſallye to hinder Zorobabel and the reſt: and that in theſe wordes, <hi>let vs build</hi> &amp;c, when they intended to ſuppla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. The other is, their lying Hipocriſie, <hi>we ſeke as you, we ſacrifiſe as you:</hi> and firſte it is ſtrange to ſée the agréement of the godleſſe. Againſte true Mycheas, the whole rabble of falſe prophetes prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied good to king Achab. When the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple wanted water in the wylderneſſe, the texte ſayth: <hi>conuenerunt aduerſus Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen &amp; Aaronem.</hi> Ioſue <hi>11.</hi> Againſt Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael both Iabin king of Hazor, and Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bab king of Madon, and the king of Shimro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and the king of Achſhaph, and the kings that were by the North in the mountaines, the Cananites both by Eaſte and Weaſt, the Amorites, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thits, I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>buſits, Phorezites, with al their hoaſt as the ſand in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſea ſhore for mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituds pitched to fight againſt Iſraell.</p>
            <p>The kings of the earth ſtande vp, and the rulers take counſel togither, againſt the Lorde and againſte his annoynted:
<pb facs="tcp:8123:7"/>Manaſſes againſt Ephraim, Ephraim againſte Manaſſes, and both agaynſte Iudah. Phariſies againſt Saduces, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duces againſte Phariſies, and yet both againſt Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Herode againſt Pilate, Pilate againſt Herode, and yet in Chriſtes death <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch is reconcyled to other. Theſe Samaritans were of diuerſe ſectes, and yet al againſt the buylding of the temple.</p>
            <p>Among all the falſe Prophetes not one to take Micheas part, nor among al the people, one to aunſwere for Moſes, nor among al the kings any one that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured Ioſua, not one Phariſie, not one Saducey, to aſſiſt Chriſte, not ſo muche as one Samaritane, to ſet foreward the buylding of the temple.</p>
            <p>I ſay with <hi>Tertul de preſcript: Nihil enim interest illis, licet diuerſa tractantibus, dum ad vnius veritatis expugnationem omnes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpirent:</hi> It ſkilleth not how diuerſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters they intreate of, ſo long as they conſpyre all togyther to the rootyng oute of one Truethe. Rauenyng
<pb facs="tcp:8123:8"/>Wolues although eche wil teare other, yet euery one ſéeketh the ſlaughter of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Lambe.</p>
            <p>Gréedy Kyghts albeit they wil fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fight for their pray, yet al ſéeke to kill the Chicke.</p>
            <p>Common robbers, although euerye one thinketh an other to haue too much, yet none wyl ſuffer the poore true man to ſcape ſcotfrée. Light and Darkneſſe, Chriſt and Belial, Heauen and Hel can neuer agrée togither.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſuperſtitious conſpirers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Iudah &amp; Beniamin, ſhew to al chriſtian princes, to al good magiſtrats, to all faythfull people, what they are to looke for at the handes of this world: if not open reſiſtaunce, yet falſe vndermi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: if in one hand fire of zeale, in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther water of diſcourage: in one hande bread to comfort, in the other a ſtone to ſtrike: if honour in lippes, yet diſhonor in hart.</p>
            <p>If whatſoeuer things be written, are written for our inſtruction, if all that
<pb facs="tcp:8123:8"/>haue euer attempted reformation of Gods houſe with Zorobabel, haue ben troubled with Samaritanes: if the firſt Abell in his ſacrifice with a blouddy Cain: if Daniel with falſe worſhippers: if all the true Prophetes, with manye falſe Prophetes: if Iohn Baptiſt with a generation of vypers: if Chriſt Ieſus with Scribes, Phariſies, and Saduces: if the Apoſtles, with Iewes, Stoyckes, and Epicures: if Conſtantine the great with Arrius: if Theodoſius with Macedonius and Neſtorius: if Marcia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with Eutiches: if the Children of this world be in their generation wiſer than the children of light: if thoſe that ſéeke to pleaſe God ſhall be ſure to offend men: then ſurely hath Zorobabel no cauſe to maruell at the ſtrange conſpiracies dayly practiſed againſt Chriſt and hys Goſpel. What though they frette and fume? what though they appoynt holye leagues and name their generals? Let them ſéeke to make hauocke of the flock of Chriſt, &amp; lyke wylde Boares to roote
<pb facs="tcp:8123:9"/>out the vyne Ieſus, and that the name of God be no more named: yet as long as he that dwelleth in heauen laugheth them to ſcorne, ſo long ſhal Dauid with his ſlyng braine Golyath, and little Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon with his goade, and Sampſon with his Iaw-bone ſlay thouſands. Better is one that feareth the Lord, than a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand wicked, and greater is he that is on our ſide, than he that is againſt vs.</p>
            <p>Let them tearme vs Heretickes and Schiſmatickes, yet with that whyche they call Hereſie do we worſhippe the true God of our fathers: Let them blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme vs, and ſpeake all euill of Zoro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>babel: wel, let looſers haue theyr words, they haue loſte a greate parte of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome (the Lordes name be prayſed, he hath wonne them to himſelfe) let vs pray, Confirme this O Lord y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou haſt wrought in vs, that thy wayes maye be knowen vpon earth, thy ſauing health among al nations.</p>
            <p>Let them nowe put in practiſe theyr late Tridentine aduiſe, let the Diuell
<pb facs="tcp:8123:9"/>be muche madder than heretofore, leffe there be more trouble vnder the goſpell than vnder ignorant popery: for why? Apoca. <hi>12.</hi> Wo be to the inhabitantes of the Earth, and of the ſea, for the Diuell is come downe and hath greate wrath, knowing that his tyme is but ſhort, his practiſes are diſcloſed, hys vyſor is plucked off, his blinde Ceremonies are al abandoned, his Locuſtes, his Graſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoppers, his Monkes, his Friers, are al ſwallowed vp.</p>
            <p>He that doth euill, hateth the light, the théefe can not abide the candle, hys gold is but copper it cannot abyde the touchſtone, his gauled backe maye not be touched without winſing, his blea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red eyes can not abyde the bright ſunne beames of Chriſtes Goſpell. At the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it may appeare, what bloudye conflictes he rayſed by his miniſters, as the ſhedding of Innocents bloud, as the corporall poſſeſſion and vexation of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny with vncleane ſpirites, of priuie hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering, (as bere) of open withſtanding
<pb facs="tcp:8123:10"/>(as to Elyas, Ieremy, Mycheas, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, Iohn Baptiſt, Chriſt Ieſus, his Apoſtles, yea &amp; in the primatiue church in ten bloudy perſecutions, and al thys) vntill he had filled himſelfe with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proche of Gods Saints. But after that this aduerſarie had (as it ſéemed) got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten a little victorie, &amp; had obſcured (with a foggy miſt) the cleare light of the goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, and as the God of this world ruled in the children of vnbeliefe, wythout checke or controlement, then had he ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure to lull the world aſléepe in reache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecuritie. Then rayſed he vp ſtro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g illuſions, of the liues and deathes of Saintes, of wonderfull myracles wrought by their reliques, of gogglyng eyes, of ſalt teares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deade ſtockes, of ſtrange operation, of ſtrange blouds, of the vnſufferable paynes of purgatory, of pilgrimages, of walking ſpirites, of vggly and feareful ghoſtes: yea and in the latter age, of Hob-gobblin, of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin goodfellow: very ſtartlebugges, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſcare crowes: and with theſe his
<pb facs="tcp:8123:10"/>practiſes bewitched he al that drunke of the cuppe of his abhomination, by the ſpace almoſt of ſeauen hundreth yeares laſt paſt.</p>
            <p>But after that it pleaſed God of his great and rich mercy to take the candle from vnder the buſhell, and to drawe that two edged ſword of his word, that deuideth betwéene the bones and the marrowe, then was that man of ſin re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Babylon layde waſte, his kingdom the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> draweth to an end, hys Empyre is abridged, a ſtronger man poſſeſſeth the houſe. His rage and fury is therfore the greater, eſpecially now that he ſéeth that the dayes are ſhortned for the elect ſake, he now beſtirreth him ſelfe, for he knoweth his tyme is but ſhort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r. lib. <hi>1.</hi> de ſummo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ono. T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto crude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liùs perſequitur, vt qui ſe damnandum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uit, vt ſibi ſocios multiplicet quibuſeum ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nnae ignibus addicatur.</hi> He perſecuteth ſo muche the more cruellye, that as hée knoweth himſelfe ſure to be damned, ſo
<pb facs="tcp:8123:11"/>he may multiplie fellowes, to partake the paynes of hell fire.</p>
            <p>He that in olde tyme beganne with deceyte, he nowe endeth with deceyte, he beganne with bloud, he now endeth with bloud.</p>
            <p>He that made Adam to loſe Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, he maketh many to forſake their owne natiue countrey: him for an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, them for leſſe than the paryng: hée that made Adam diſobey God, he ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them to diſobey the Lordes an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed: he that made Lots wife looke backe to Sodome, he now maketh olde Engliſh beldams to returne after, xix. yéeres preachyng of the Goſpell, to the lothſome puddle of Popiſhe trumperie: He that in old tyme by the bloud of the Lambe was ouercome and diſpoſſeſſed of heauen, he by a droppe of bloud is contente to take poſſeſſion of his wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and Sorcerers here on earthe: He that in olde tyme ſhedde the bloud of innocent Abell, and prepared hoate fornaſſes for Goddes faythfull ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants,
<pb facs="tcp:8123:11"/>hée at this daye rayſeth vppe bloudie maſſacres and firie inquiſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, and why? but bycauſe hys tyme is ſhorte.</p>
            <p>Where the Goſpel is preached moſt diligently, there dothe the Deuill rage moſte furiouſly, and lyke a good Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne endeuoreth by all meanes to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edifie thoſe walles that the worde of God hath battered downe, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new that olde Adam, that by the ſpirite of God is put away, and (as one ſayde) Account al tyme loſte that is not ſpent in ſome vertuous exercyſe: ſo the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill accounteth all tyme loſt, that is not ſpent either in veryng, or withdrawing from God the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: and why? but bicauſe his time is ſhorte.</p>
            <p>A ſeconde thing in theſe idolatrous Samaritanes, is their lying &amp; falſe hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, for neither ſought they y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord as Iſrael did, neither ſacrificed they as they ought to haue done. <hi>2.</hi> Reg. <hi>17.</hi> they prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded to feare y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord, but apointed prieſts of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues for the high places,
<pb facs="tcp:8123:12"/>and prepared ſacrifice, and did after the maner of the nations, and therefore the ſpirite of God teſtifyeth, that they ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther feared God, nor did after the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nauntes, nor cuſtome, nor lawe, nor co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement which the Lord co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the children of Iacob, whome he na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Iſraell: notwithſtanding here they come with theſe lying ſpeches, <hi>we ſeke, we ſacrifice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Singular was y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> impudency of theſe Samaritanes, that notwithſtanding their owne conſciences accuſed them, &amp; their dayly practiſes declared the cleane contrary, yet they bluſh not to ſaye <hi>wee ſeke.</hi> &amp;c. It is a plague that lyeth on Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrytes: there is no other ſinner, be he neuer ſo ſtrong a thiefe; be he neuer ſo filthy a liuer, be he neuer ſo common a lyar, be he neuer ſo great a blaſphemer, be he neuer ſo byting an vſurer, be he neuer ſo cruel a murtherer, be he neuer ſo rancke a traytor, be he neuer ſo falſe to God, ſo faithleſſe to men: but in his thefte be deſireth darkneſſe, in his adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb facs="tcp:8123:12"/>ſecretnes, for his lying pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for his blaſphemy ſometyme ſéeketh forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, in hys vſury feareth lawe, in hys murder dreadeth the wagging of euery leafe, in his treaſon ſuſpecteth the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wraying of the byrdes of the ayre.</p>
            <p>But the Hypocrite (neyther fearing him that knoweth the hart and raynes, neyther regarding his owne reproche) dareth, bycauſe he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bleare mens eies, to preſent himſelfe (as it were) into the preſence of God. Suche were they that came to our ſauiour Chriſt, Maiſter we know thou ſpeakeſt truth, and regardeſt no mans perſon, is it lawful to pay try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to Ceſar or no? Why, if I ſpeake truth, beléeue you me not oh ye Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites? and another: Maiſter what ſhal I do to inherite eternal life: and, Mayſter what is the greateſt commaundemente in the law?</p>
            <p>To whome our ſauiour aunſwereth, Not euery one that ſayth to me Lorde, Lorde, ſhall enter into the kingdome of heauen, but he which doth the wil of my
<pb facs="tcp:8123:13"/>father which is in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Why do you call me Lord, Lorde, and doe not the things which I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunde? why tempt yée me O ye hypocrites? what offer ye to me O ye painted ſepulchers? you ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare fayre outwardly, but inwardly yée are full of dead mens bones, and all filthyneſſe. Why doe yée honour mée with your lippes, your hartes beyng farre from me? Why ſpeake you lies vnto me, you haue conſciences marked with an hoate Iron? Why pretend you a ſhewe of godlineſſe, ſeyng you haue denied the power thereof? Surely theſe Samaritanes are as it were a cleare glaſſe to beholde the miſerie of iniquitie that in this worlde preuayleth. Such an hypocrite was Herode, that when he purpoſed nothing but the death of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſte, as may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare by the ſlaughter of the innocents, yet he perſwadeth with the Wiſemen, to returne home by him, that he with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might worſhip him, that was borne King of the Iewes: ſuch falſe teachers
<pb facs="tcp:8123:13"/>hurte the Apoſtles, ſuche falſe brethren added muche to Paules bondes. And died theſe Samaritanes only thinke we with Zorobabel? and roſe there none of their aſhes? &amp; are there at this daye no Herodians that in word ſpeake that in harte they thinke not? &amp; are there no falſe teachers to hinder the Goſpell of Chriſte? and are there no falſe brethren to adde to Paules bondes?</p>
            <p>Not to ſpeake of ſuch as whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Steuen preached ſtopped their eares: nor of ſuch as ſay we wil not heare, charme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer neuer ſo wiſely: nay there are a broode which liue in the church, &amp; by the church, but are not of the churche, that at this day do hinder, and hitherto haue hindred the courſe of Zorobabel.</p>
            <p>And as true it is, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> new wine is not to be put in olde bottels, nor new cloth to be patched in an old garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, nor Chriſt &amp; Circumciſion to be matched togither; and as God in olde age rayſed vp not a Prieſte of Baal but Elias, nor our ſauiour any lerned Phariſée, but ſimple
<pb facs="tcp:8123:14"/>fiſhermen, to treade the waye of hys Goſpel: ſo is not Zorobabel to admitte ſuch as mingle Chriſt and Belial, the Church of God and Idols, the Goſpell and popery, religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and mockery. What better words than of Samaritanes, <hi>we ſeeke, we ſacrifice:</hi> what better profeſſion than of Herode, Go and ſéeke and bryng me word that I may worſhip: yet were the Samaritanes Idolatours, yet was Herode a Foxe. What better ſpéeches, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>formable men, we obſerue our princes laws, we follow iniunctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, we obey orders: yet if it come to exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation at the paſſage of Iordan, (as Iepthe and the Gyleadites did trie the Ephraimites, by pronouncing <hi>Shiboleth</hi>) I feare me, they wil ſay ſingle <hi>Siboleth,</hi> there wil want the harty aſpiration <hi>(h) (h)</hi> wanteth, the harte wanteth.</p>
            <p>It is an olde prouerbe, <hi>Ex vnguibus leonem.</hi> Let them be narowly loked into, howe they grunt and grone at the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the Goſpell: howe they carpe at the doings of the godlye lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned:
<pb facs="tcp:8123:14"/>how they deride the ſimpler ſorte of the profeſſors of the Goſpell: how open eares they haue to heare, and how rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye tongues to miſlike the ſtate of oure Churche: what ſecreate conuenticles they haue: howe they daylye buzze of ſtrange newes: howe big they looke on the profeſſors of the Goſpell: howe they ſtill retayne one Maſſe tricke or other to put the people in minde: how willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they will maintaine groſſe Popery, but for diſputation ſake only.</p>
            <p>If you looke narrowly into them, you ſhall perceiue them to be plaine Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, playne Herodians, the one ready to hinder the building of the houſe of God, the other lyke craftye Foxes, to eate vppe the lambe Ieſus.</p>
            <p>God that is not deceyued will vomit out all thoſe luke warme Souldiors, he cannot abide ſuche as can couer Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes crueltie with Catoes grauitie, nor ſuche as to hide Herodes butcherie, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende Iohn Baptiſtes ſimplicitie.</p>
            <p>Theſe leaues wythout fruite, theſe
<pb facs="tcp:8123:15"/>eares without corne, theſe clouds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out water, theſe lampes without oyle, as they haue liued without feare, ſo ſhall they dye without hope, and as they haue bodies without life, ſo haue they ſoules without God. As Copper reſembleth Gold, &amp; is nothing leſſe, as ſtage players do ofte put on another perſon than their own, as in the Rainebow there appeare many colours, when in déede there are none at all, as in broken glaſſes, where there is neuer a face, yet there appeare two faces: ſo in theſe double faced <hi>Ianuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> in theſe cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geable <hi>Chamaeleons</hi> ther is nothing leſſe, than that which ſéemeth moſt to be. What though they ſay, <hi>they ſeeke, they ſacrifice:</hi> let them bragge of their forwardneſſe: we know that emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Tubbes do euer make the greateſte ſound. A freſh Iuy doth not always ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nify the beſt wine. The Cypers trée is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talleſt trée, but it beareth leaſte fruite. Bladders puffed vppe with winde, are good for nothing but to make footballes.</p>
            <p>I can compare theſe hypocrites to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb facs="tcp:8123:15"/>ſo fitly, as to the Diſtridge, who (when there was a contention betwene the byrdes and foure footed beaſts) to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the byrds, ſhewed his bil &amp; wings, and to deceiue the beaſts put forthe hys hoofe, ſo ſeeking to pleaſe both, deceiued both. And as Auſtin ſaide of ſome, while they will be Iewes and Chriſtians, they are neither Iews nor Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſo theſe whyle they wil be Papiſtes and Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts, they are neither Papiſts nor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants. Yet they ſay, <hi>we ſeeke, we ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice,</hi> we loue the Lord with al our hart, with all our ſoule, with al our ſtrength: But if they once maye warme them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues at the highe Prieſtes fyre, they will foreſweare wyth Peter: if a little ſtorme of affliction ryſe, they wyll goe backe in the tyme of trouble: if you bid them ſell all they haue, they will eyther with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> yongma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> departe heauy, or wyth Ananias &amp; his wife kepe back half: they wyll embrace the worlde, wyth De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas: they wyll forſake the Apoſtle, with Himeneus and Philetus: they wil
<pb facs="tcp:8123:16"/>perſecute with Alexander: I pray God they do not ſell w<hi rend="sup">c</hi> Iudas. And yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding al this, ſuch is their ſham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſneſſe, that as in hearte they ſéeke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the ouerthrowe of Chriſtes Kingdome, ſo in worde they pretend no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as to ſerue God, and to ſacrifice vnto hym. And thus much as touching the conſente and hipocriſy.</p>
            <p>The ſecond parte of this texte, is the anſwere, wherin there are foure things in order worth the conſideration.</p>
            <p>Fyrſte the vnitie of the aunſwerers, Zorobabel, Ioſue, and the reſte of the chiefe fathers of Iſraell, and a flatte de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall, <hi>It is not for you, but for vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the agréement of them in building, <hi>wee oure ſelues, and wee togyther.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdely, what they will builde, <hi>a houſe to the Lorde God of Iſraell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, the warrant whereby they builde, <hi>as Kyng Cyrus the King of Perſia hath commaunded vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for the firſte: the aunſwere was
<pb facs="tcp:8123:16"/>not of one, but of Zorobabel, Ioſue, and the reſte of the chéefe fathers of Iſrael: wherein wee learne, that in matters of weight, there oughte not to take place Zorobabels own opinion, but it muſte be aided with the conſente of others, <hi>ſic volo, ſic rubeo,</hi> muſt haue no place in Gods matters.</p>
            <p>They aunſwere not as the Datorſe in tyme of Poperye did to a reaſonable demaund, The Popes holineſſe will not admitte it, and if his holyneſſe woulde, yet my Lorde woulde not ſuffer it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> as his name importethe (by interpretation) to one ſtraunge and farre from confuſion, and althoughe in thys refuſall he be a very Preciſian, yet he is not ſingular. He aunſwereth not, it is for you and mee, but ioyning hym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe wyth the reſte, <hi>It is not for you and vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here are many thinges, that if tyme and place would ſuffer, would require long tractation. As firſte, that Zoroba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels refuſall and the reſte, doth teache
<pb facs="tcp:8123:17"/>vs, that aide of the Idolatrouſe, of the wicked, although it be offred, is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, eſpecially in matters touching the building of Gods houſe.</p>
            <p>Abraham refuſed to take of the King of Sodom, ſo much as a thréed or a ſhoe lachet, leaſte he ſhould ſay: I haue enri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched Abraham. The yong Prophet for eating breade with the wicked old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet was deuoured of a Lion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theodorus li. <hi>2.</hi> ca. <hi>6.</hi> Eccleſ. Hist.</hi> repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth, that Liberius going into baniſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, refuſed al gifts of the Emperour and hys wife, let them giue theſe (ſayth he) to Auxentius &amp; Epictetus their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian heretikes.</p>
            <p>Secondly, here we learne by this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that the company and leagues of the wicked are vtterly to be ſhaken off. For bleſſed is the man that doeth not walke in the counſell of the wicked, nor ſtande in the way of ſinners, nor ſitte in the ſeate of the ſcornefull.</p>
            <p>He that toucheth pitche ſhall be defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led wyth it, one ſhéepe infecteth a whole
<pb facs="tcp:8123:17"/>flocke, one ſparckle kindleth a greate flame, and one infected houſe is able to poyſon a whole Citie. There is no par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticipation of righteouſneſſe and vnrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>Iohn the Euangeliſte woulde not waſhe in the bathe wherin Cherinthus the enimy of the truthe bathed himſelf. Caius and Alexander being condemned to die, &amp; being led to execution with cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Marcioniſtes, made an eſpeciall requeſte to their tormentors, that they might be ſlayne aſyde from thoſe Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cioniſts, and that their bloud might not in death be mingled with theirs, wyth whome in life they agréed not in reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, here may be obſerued to our ſingular comforte, that the Lord diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth to his ſeruants, the counſells of the wicked, and ouerturneth the practiſes of hys enimies againſt hym and his chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, as of Achitophel, Hamman, Herod, &amp; the reſt. The thing y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> here is eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be weighed, is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> reſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moued Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabel
<pb facs="tcp:8123:18"/>and the reſt: and that is, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> they would not haue the true ſeruice of God mingled with Idolatrous or ſtraunge worſhippe.</p>
            <p>They enuyed not that theſe Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans ſhoulde ſerue the Lorde, they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired nothing more, than that the Lorde myght faithfully and religiouſly be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, but therefore did they deny them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parte or felowſhippe in this worke, bicauſe they worſhipped ſtrange Gods, erected Idolles, and put their truſte and confidence in creatures.</p>
            <p>The God of Iſraell can not abide to be worſhipped with other Gods, and therefore althoughe they pretended as you heare, yet that God, that is worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped in ſpirite and truth, would not haue hys ſeruauntes to admitte theſe hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites.</p>
            <p>God requireth the whole hearte, the whole ſoule, the whole mynde. Hee that made the whole man, wil not be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with halfe man: God is a iealous God, and will not deuide with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill.
<pb facs="tcp:8123:18"/>If God be God, honor him, if Baul be God honor him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lactan, de falſa Relig. Lib. <hi>1.</hi> Ca. <hi>19.</hi> Si ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor idem tribuitur alijs, ipſe omnino non coli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, cuim religio eſt, illum eſſe vnum ac ſolum verum credere:</hi> If the ſame honor be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to others, he at all is not worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped, whoſe religion is, to belée us hym to be one, and hym alone to be true.</p>
            <p>We muſte not plowe wyth an Oxe and an Aſſe, nor ſowe our grounde with diuers Séedes, nor make our garments of Linſey Wolſey.</p>
            <p>Howe long ſhall wee halte on bothe ſides? What agréement haue Chriſt and Belial? if ye wil be circumciſed, then is Chriſte dead in vaine: if you will bee iuſtifyed by the Lawe, then are you fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len from Grace. Yee cannot ſerue twoo Maiſters, yee cannot ſerue God and Mammon. Chriſte ſayeth not, it is not conuenient to ſerue two maiſters, nor it is not profitable, but by an argument of impoſſibilitie, Ye cannot.</p>
            <p>Such Samaritans had Zorobabel, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8123:19"/>notwithſtanding that the ſpirite of God putteth down an impoſſibilitie, yet wold ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>they ſought, that they ſacrificed &amp;c.</hi> that although they loued in harte Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrie and ſuperſtition, and that neither would haue the Prieſts reade, nor the Prophets expound the law, neither wold themſelues eate of the Paſſeouer, nor ſuffer their childrens forſkinne to be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed: yet with ſhameleſſe face, with lying tongs and falſe harts, woulde ſaye they did loue Zorobabel. If the ſonne ſhal riſe againſt his father, the father a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his ſonne: if the daughter againſt hir mother, and the daughter in lawe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt hir mother in law. If Cicero ſaid that Philoſophy did firſt vnite men into one body, but we knowe it was God by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> mighty power of his word: truly then if with Infidels no ſocietie, but through Philoſophy, then with vs no true obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence towards the Lordes annointed, no faithfull loue among brethren, where there is not concord in true &amp; ſound reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion The iarre about religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
<pb facs="tcp:8123:19"/>iar, &amp; the bond of religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt bond. Let them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> come, &amp; tell Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabel, truly <hi>we will build with you,</hi> wée wil kéepe back your enimies, we wil ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute your laws, wee will liue like good ſubiects, but (as for our conſciences) wée cannot abide the talke of thys God that only wil be ſerued, wee cannot abide to be preſent at your prayers, wee can not partake of your Communion. Did not theſe Samaritanes lye when they ſaide, <hi>we ſeeke, we ſacrifice,</hi> &amp; ſhal we think theſe ſpeak truth? Wel, it is wel ſayde in my texte, <hi>Zorobabel, Ioſue, and the chiefe fathers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Iſraell, he and al his counſell anſwered, It is not for you and vs.</hi> Truſt you? nay not for a Denyre, he that gathereth not with vs, ſcattereth abroade: hee that is not wyth me (ſayth our ſauiour) he is againſt me. Now can he be faithful to ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe to God. The Iſralites admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted neither Iewe nor Proſelite, not ſo muche as once to come among them, vnleſſe he firſt were circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued Moſes law, &amp; had bin partaker of
<pb facs="tcp:8123:20"/>their ſacrifices, Zorobabel here refuſeth all their offred ſeruice: Is it then like, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> eyther y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Iſralites, or Zorobabel, would eyther haue putte them in great auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, or haue gyuen them leaue to haue liued after their conſciences? Nay, hee that woulde not allowe them for theyr ſuperſtition to helpe to laye lyme and ſtone, woulde not allowe them to lyue after their owne Idolatry. Hee woulde not gyue them leaue to goe to the Diuel. He that ſaid, do that only that I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; decline not either to the right or to the left hand, but, <hi>ad legem &amp; ad teſtimonia,</hi> to the Law and to the teſtimonies. He had ſo inſtructed Zorobabel, that he woulde not yéelde, and had ſo terrifyed the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritans, that they durſt not aſke, but whatſoeuer inwardly they mente, out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly they ſay: <hi>Let vs builde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It had beene a ſhamefull thing for the Samaritans, not onely not to haue proffered aide, but to haue gone aboute priuily to vndermine, and to haue cra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued leaue, in that his painefull buſineſſe,
<pb facs="tcp:8123:20"/>to haue layne in a corner repyning at hys indeuor: But to haue iudged hys conſcience, naye to haue condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned hym, nay to poure oute prayers for his ennimyes, to accompte hym a Schiſmatike, his Heretikes, his worke wickedneſſe, his building confuſion, to harbor, nay with mony to ſupporte hys enimies, had bin deteſtable, had bin diue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>liſh. Anſwere me O ye Samarita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, ſhal not Zorobabel giue you leaue to robbe men by the high way ſide, and dare you aſke leaue to rob God of his honor? ſhal not Zorobabel giue you leaue to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitte murther of others, and ſhall hee ſuffer you to kil your own ſoules: Shall he not licence you (althoughe your Pope do) to open adulteries and kéeping con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubines, and ſhall he ſuffer you to make your bodies, the temples of God, ſlaues to Idolles ſacrifice? Shall hee not ſuffer any high treaſon againſt himſelfe, and ſhal he winke at ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blaſphemy againſt God? Anſwere me O ye Samaritanes.</p>
            <p>If old father Chriſoſtome now liued,
<pb facs="tcp:8123:21"/>he would tell the people of Antioch, that they bounde horſes and fettered them, and with hornes poured in medicine, and ſhall they ſuffer theyr brethren to run on headlong into iniquitie.</p>
            <p>If father Auſten now liued, he would tell Gaudentius, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> it ſéemeth vnto you y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the vnwilling are not to be compelled to heare: you are much deceyued, for while you compell them againſte theyr wyll, you often tymes make them willyng.</p>
            <p>Is it behoofefull for the common wealth, that no manne abuſe hys owne houſe or horſe, for that if they pleaſe not hym, they may profitte others? and ſhall it not be behoofefull that no man abuſe hys owne ſoule?</p>
            <p>You are not your owne, you are bou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghte neither with golde nor ſiluer, but wyth the precious bloude of the imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culate Lambe Chriſte Ieſus.</p>
            <p>But O Sir, it is for their conſcience, be good to them, ſhew mercy.</p>
            <p>I wil ſhewe thée (O Man) ſayeth the Prophet, what it is to doe good, it is to
<pb facs="tcp:8123:21"/>loue Iuſtice, and to ſhew mercye.</p>
            <p>Iehu might haue ſuffred y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Baalites, Ioſias &amp; Ezechias the Idolatours: wel they myghte haue ſhewed mercy, but ſure they ſhoulde not haue done iuſtice.</p>
            <p>Saul ſpared Achab, Achab ſpared Benadab, Elye winked at his ſons wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, but it was to them all occaſion of ruine.</p>
            <p>Salomon ſuffred hys concubines and wiues to haue Temples, to ſerue Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tartes, Chamos, and ſtrange Gods, but the renting of Gods ſeruice rente hys Kingdome, halfe to his owne ſonne, and halfe to Ieroboam the ſon of Nebathe.</p>
            <p>Peter might haue ſpared Simon the ſorcerer, and Paule the inceſtuous Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians, but what mercy had this bin?</p>
            <p>I am of this opinion, that if I ſée one ready to drowne hymſelfe, and ſtay him not if I may, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I am giltie of his death.</p>
            <p>If I féed not one readye to dye wyth famine, hauing food wherwithal, I haue killed hym.</p>
            <p>Cicero ſayde, that hée that when
<pb facs="tcp:8123:22"/>hee maye defende iniury, if he do it not, is no leſſe in faulte tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if he forſake hys parents or countrey.</p>
            <p>He that ſaide, ſay not ſomuch as good morrow, or haile ſir, but let him bee as an Ethnicke and Publibane to thée, he would not admit him to eate at his bord that would not eate and drinke at Gods borde. But he is my friend. But Chryſt anſwereth, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> will of my father in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, he is my father, my mother, my brother, my ſiſter. Cicero ſayth, that y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is the ſureſt frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dſhip which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſimilitude of good maners hathe coupled. You know the Prouerbe, No couſin in Courte, No couſin in Cheapeſide: ſo ſurely it ought to be, No Chriſtian in the Churche, no Couſin in Court. If thy hand or foote of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thée cut the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> off, if thine eie, pul it out, this may (I denye not) be wel vnderſtood literally, for we vſe to cut off rotten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, <hi>ne pars ſincera trahatur:</hi> but it is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>déede mente of them that are vnto vs in ſtéede of theſe parts, of hands, of féete, of eies, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> is, moſt neare &amp; familiar friends,
<pb facs="tcp:8123:22"/>if they goe about to draw vs or to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vs from Chriſt, whom to knowe is eternal life.</p>
            <p>O but he hath done me good. Pharaos daughter nurſed Moyſes, the hungrye Rauens fed Elyas.</p>
            <p>But alas ſhal I render euil for hys good? ſhal I not loue my neyghbour as my ſelf? ſhal I ſuffer him <hi>cum ratione in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanire?</hi> his father dyd me good: ſhoulde Moyſes haue reſerued Pharan for hys daughters ſake?</p>
            <p>To end this point, it is euident, that what proteſtation ſoeuer theſe Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritanes made, yea ſo long as they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped Idolles, ſo long Zorobabel would not truſt them, no nor vouchaſafe them ſo much countenance, as once to number them among ſuche as hewed ſtones or made morter.</p>
            <p>But what if they had denyed? he was not ignoraunt, that if in the colde winter, in the time of gracious Cirus, the ſnake might haue warmed himſelfe by his or the elders fiers of Iſrael, that
<pb facs="tcp:8123:23"/>then he would at ſpring of the yeare, if not haue bitten, yet haue hiſſed at Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robabell. But anſwere me O ye En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Samaritanes, O ye recuſantes that diſhonour God and diſobey the Lords annoynted, ſhal a ſtrange proud Italian Prieſt withdrawe you? what hath the churche of England offended you? wherein haue we corrupted the goſpell of Ieſus Chriſt? who flieth to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> touchſtone of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures, you or we?</p>
            <p>Offendeth it you that the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are in our mother tong, and are knowen to the Lay people, blame your owne Doctours: euen <hi>Nicolaus Lyra</hi> and <hi>Caietanus in. <hi>14. 1</hi> Corin.</hi> do teache, that it was the manner of the primatiue Church, and that out of this doctrine of Paul may be gathered, that it is better to the edifying of the church, that pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blike prayers maye be in a tongue knowen to the people, than to be ſayde in Latine of the Prieſte and Clarkes.</p>
            <p>Offendeth it you (and that is the matter) that wée denie Tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb facs="tcp:8123:23"/>the Real preſence? blame your owne Doctors, for Bonauenture, Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rande, Scotus, Thomas, hold foure ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall opinions. It is an opinion ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer heard of vntil the Laterane cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel, <hi>1215</hi> yeares after Chriſte.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Rupertus abbas Tutienſis</hi> confeſſeth, that before that Counſell it was law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to belieue or not to beleue. Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall late Byſhop of Durham. <hi>li. <hi>1.</hi> de Euchariſtia, De modo quo idfieret, ſatius for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſſe erat, curioſum quemque ſuae relinquere coniecturae, ſicut licitum fuit ante conſilium Lateranum.</hi> Of the manner howe thys ſhoulde come to paſſe, it had bene beſte to haue lefte euery curious man to his owne coniecture, as it was lawfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Laterane counſell.</p>
            <p>Offendeth it you that we denie the Pope to be Vniuerſal byſhop? Blame your own Pope Gregorie, for he ſaith: <hi>Nemo predeceſſorum meorum &amp;c.</hi> none of my predeceſſours euer tooke vpon him this name of ſingularitie, this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, this po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pouſe, this proude name.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:24"/>
            <p>Offendeth it you that we preache a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Purgatorie: blame not vs but your owne Doctours. For Gregorye your owne Pope ſayth, it is as it were in hote bathes: Alcuinus ſayth, it is in the ayre, ſome in yſe, ſome in ſhadow of trées.</p>
            <p>The fathers in their late Triden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine counſel confeſſe, that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny things vncertain, which haue a ſhew of falſehoode, which tende to curioſity, and to vayn ſuperſtition, and which ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of filthy lucre.</p>
            <p>Youre ſchoolemen are togither by the eares, whether the Pope be more mercyful than Chriſt (ſéeing that it is not reade that euer he releaſed from y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> paynes of Purgatory) and whether the Pope maye emptye Purgatory at his pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Offendeth it you, that we deny pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and inuocation of Sainctes? blame your owne doctour Eckius, who after much ſayde for that matter, concludeth thus: <hi>Explicitè non eſt praecepta ſanctorum
<pb facs="tcp:8123:24"/>inuocatio in ſacris literis.</hi> Inuocation or prayer to ſaintes is not commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in holye ſcriptures: not in the olde Teſtament, bycauſe the people were otherwiſe too too propenſe into Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trye: and the fathers were in <hi>Limbo,</hi> not yet bleſſed: nor in the new Teſtament, leaſt the people might ſéeme to be led to the worſhippe of erthly creatures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne: and if the Apoſtles and Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſtes ſhould haue taught this, they ſhoulde haue ben accounted arrogant, as though they had ſought for this glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye after their death.</p>
            <p>Offendeth it you, that we pul downe Images? blame youre owne Doctour Barnarde, who <hi>ad Guil: abbatem Clunia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſ. Quem ex ijs fructum requirimus &amp;c.</hi> What fruite looke you for of them, whiche ſerue for nothing, but eyther to féede fooles, or to ſeduce the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
            <p>Offendeth it you that you maye not haue the Popes pardon? that you maye not be abſolued <hi>à pena &amp; culpa?</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:8123:25"/>blame good father Ierome, who vppon the. <hi>16.</hi> of Matthew, <hi>Quorum remiſeritis peccata: Iſtum locum Epiſcopi &amp; Presbyteri non intelligentes &amp;c.</hi> This place biſhops and Prieſtes vnderſtanding not, take vpon them ſomewhat of the Phariſées pryde to abſolue or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne, where as before the Lord, not the ſentence of the prieſt, but the life of the ſinner is to be regarded. Offendeth it you that wée burne and diſgrace your <hi>Legenda aurea,</hi> blame Ludouicus Viues, for he ſaithe, <hi>Non video cur dici poſsit aurea &amp;c.</hi> I ſee not why it can be ſayd to be of gold, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is written of a man of an Iron face, and a leaden harte.</p>
            <p>What looke you for O ye Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanes? For your deuiſes of menne, we preach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> goſpel, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> power of God to ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation to all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> beleue it. For your Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, we ſhew in our Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords death vntil he come. For your Pope Chriſtes vicar, we preach y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy ghoſt to be vicare general, which doth teach vs al truth. For your pick purſe
<pb facs="tcp:8123:25"/>Purgatory, we preach that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bloud of Ieſus Chriſte doth clenſe vs from all ſinne. For your many mediatours, your poore helps, we teach that there is but one mediatour betwene God and men, Ieſus Chriſte bothe God &amp; Man.</p>
            <p>For your Trentals of Maſſes, your Bulles of lead, your Lambes of waxe, we preache the Lion of the tribe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hudah, &amp; that Chriſt by one oblation of himſelf, once for al, hath perfitted them that be ſanctified, &amp; that the Lambe of god taketh away y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſinnes of the world.</p>
            <p>For your wodden Gods, your lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens bookes, we deliuer the worde of God, which is a Lanterne to the féete, and alight vnto the ſteppes.</p>
            <p>To co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude this part: if we haue not departed fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you vntil you haue depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God: if we haue not ſucked this of our own fingers, but drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it out of your fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taines: if for traditions of men we preache the truth of the Goſpell: if for very tri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es and traſhe, wée declare the infallible worde of life, then aryſe
<pb facs="tcp:8123:26"/>O ye Samaritanes, ſéeke the Lorde while he may be founde, walke whyle there is light, nowe is the axe layde to the roote of the trée: awake oh ye Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maritanes, it is no ſhame to amende your maners, taſt and ſée how ſwéete and pleaſaunte the Lord is.</p>
            <p>But if neyther your owne conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, nor the teſtimonies of your owne doctours, nor the difference of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines which we deliuer, nor any oure requeſtes may once moue you, behold we anſwere, <hi>It is not for you and vs to build togither,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond thing in this anſwere is, <hi>but we our ſelues togither wil buylde.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Zorobabel, Ioſue, and the reſt of the elders, as they woulde admit none but themſelues, ſo woulde they ſuffer none to buylde by hymſelfe but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gither.</p>
            <p>The Phyloſophers holde diuerſe fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſies of their <hi>ſummum bonum,</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> end, but theſe Iſralites had al but one end, one temple of the Lorde, and herein
<pb facs="tcp:8123:26"/>they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all togither.</p>
            <p>Behold it is good &amp; pleaſant (ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prophete) brethren to dwell togyther in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tie. Auſten ſaith, <hi>Ita dule<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> eſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, vt qui Pſalterum niſciunt, ipſum tamen <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſum cantent:</hi> the ſounde is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wéete, that they whiche neuer knew the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, yet ſing that Pſalme. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more acceptable to God tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, &amp; nothing more hateful tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
            <p>God is loue, Chriſte is the prince of peace, his teſtanient is a couenant and league of peace, his Angels are meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of peace, his Apoſtles were prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of peace, their whole life was an example of peace. <hi>Origen</hi> ſayde that no ſenſe without the ſcriptures, howe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſoeuer it ſéemed to be, was more to be receiued, than that golde to be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted holy whiche was without the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple: but I ſay, that there is no worke nor labour of any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any whitte to be eſtéemed, vnleſſe he obſerue the vnitie of the ſpirite in the bonde of peace.</p>
            <p>I néede not ſtand to declare the inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueniences of diſſention, the two eyes of
<pb facs="tcp:8123:27"/>Gréece, Lacedemon &amp; Athens, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> holde not togither, made Gréece a pray to hir enimies.</p>
            <p>The diſſention of Hanno and Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niball raced Carthage.</p>
            <p>The vnbrotherlike warres betwéen Etheocles and his brother Poleni<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es, decayed y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> flouriſhing ſtate of Thebes.</p>
            <p>While Ariſtobulus and Hyrcanus doe ſtriue, they ſuffer their cittie to bée ſpoyled, and their temple to bée raced.</p>
            <p>Scipio Africanus hauing ouercome y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> Numantines aſked Tyreſtas how it hapned y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Numa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tia before ſo inuincible, was at the laſte with great eaſe ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come: He anſwered, bragge not Scripio, our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>corde before made vs victors, but our diſcorde hath bred our diſtruction.</p>
            <p>Olde Micipſa on his death bedde dyd ſing his laſt <hi>cygnaea ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tio,</hi> By co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cord ſmal things increaſe, by diſcorde the greateſt come to nothing.</p>
            <p>It is much to builde togither, for as <hi>virtus vnita fortior,</hi> ſo many hands make light worke.</p>
            <p>Surely the diſſentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> about the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Gods houſe did neuer good, for
<pb facs="tcp:8123:27"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, how ſhal the day laborers do, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the maiſter workerm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n do diſſent?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Clemens Alexan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>trom:</hi> ſayth, the heathens were wont this to obic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, you Chriſtians doe diſſent among your ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo many ſectes, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they do euery one chalenge the title of Chriſtianity yet euery one doth hate and condemne Another.</p>
            <p>Chriſoſtome complayned that in his tyme the Iews were wont thus to ſay, I woulde ben Chriſtian, but I knowe not whiche parte to cleaue vnto: ſurely for this cauſe (ſayth he) we are become rediculous to the Iewes and the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, whyle the Church is rente into a thouſand partes. The diſſention be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene Peter and Paul, the departure of Paule and Barnabas, the holding of ſome of Paul, of ſome of Apollo, of ſome of Cephas, no doubt vexed the godly in the firſt primatiue Church.</p>
            <p>The quarrels betwéene Theophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus and Epiphanius, Auſten &amp; Ierome, Ierome and Ruffinus, opened manye gappes to wicked Heretickes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:28"/>
            <p>The queſtion betwéene Luther and Zwinglius aboute the ſupper of the Lorde, no doubt, hardened &amp; at this day hardneth many in the error of popery.</p>
            <p>The contention among vs aboute round &amp; ſquare, aboute white &amp; blacke, about ſitting, ſtanding, walking, knée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling at y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munion, maketh both parts of leſſe credite, and encourageth none but ſworne aduerſaries to both. We al agrée of the holſomeneſſe of the meate, &amp; why do we fall out for the diſhe? it ſkil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth not whether it be Pewter, Tinne, Siluer, Golde, or a tréen diſhe. And as long as we accompt the medicine to be ſoueraigne, why do we take exception to the bore of wood or ſtone? It is the Deuils policie to deuide vs, that he at our breach may y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more eaſily enter in.</p>
            <p>Stragling Souldiers are ſoone ſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed vp. The mouſe and the frogge may ſtriue ſo long, vntill the Kite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure both warriers. Sylurus ſonnes ſhalbe a terrour to all their enimies, ſo long as they abide in the fagotte bonde of true friendſhip: if once they ſeparate
<pb facs="tcp:8123:28"/>themſelues, they ſhal be an eaſie pray to their aduerſaries. Ariſtotle ſayde truely, that in a ciuill diſſention one e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimie armed within the Citie, is more able to hurte than many without: but we may ſay it muche more truly of the church. Let vs my brethren ſéeke thoſe things, <hi>Quaeſunt ad pacem Hieruſalem:</hi> as the Prophet fayth: Let vs pray, that as in the actes of them that beléeued there was but one harte, &amp; one ſoule, ſo that we may buylde al togither, that as all things may be done to edifying, ſo all things may be done dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly &amp; in order.</p>
            <p>The thirde thing in this their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere is, what they wil build, <hi>a houſe to the Lorde God of Iſraell.</hi> Theſe Iſraelites do in reedifying folow Salomon in his firſt buylding, for as he firſte buylded the temple before he medled with hys owne houſe, ſo theſe at the firſt deſire to erect a houſe, to buylde a temple to the Lorde their God. But what? doth the God of Iſraell delite to dwell in tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples made with handes? Albeit that euery place is méete for Chriſtians to
<pb facs="tcp:8123:29"/>make prayers in, for as Auſten ſayeth, there is no place where. God is not: if we goe vp to heauen he is there: if wée go downe to Hel he is there: if we take the wings of the winde he is there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, for himſelfe hath ſayde, beholde I am with you to the ende of the world.</p>
            <p>The houſe of God hath ſometimes bene in a ſhip on the Seas, as with our ſauiour, ſometimes in a poore houſe w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> his diſciples, ſometymes in the market place at Athens, in a parlor at Troas, on the ſhoare with Paul and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Where two or thrée are gathered togyther in my name I am in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of them, and where Chriſt is, there may we be aſſured is Chriſts Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tertul in exhorta. ad castitatem: Eccleſia eſt vbi duo aut tres ſunt, licet laici ſunt,</hi> the churche is where two or thrée be toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther although they be lay men.</p>
            <p>But God to the intente he mighte haue a peculiar place for his people, where they might vſe prayer &amp; thankeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing, &amp; offer ſacrifice, firſt raiſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon to builde, and theſe to redifye a
<pb facs="tcp:8123:29"/>houſe for his owne honour.</p>
            <p>In the bookes of kings and Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles we reade, that in the foure hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreth and foure ſcoure yeare after the children of Iſraell were come oute of Egipte, dyd Salomon builde the houſe of the Lorde of thrée ſcoure cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites long, in Ieruſalem, in mounte Moriah, whiche had bene declared vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Dauid his father, in the place which Dauid prepared, in the threſſhing floore of Ornan the Iebuſite.</p>
            <p>It is wel worth conſideration, that neyther Salomon in his firſt, nor theſe in their new buylding, do eyther builde to any other than to the Lord, or once herein thinke of buyldyng to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</p>
            <p>Salomon builded not to Abraham, although he wer the father of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, nor to Iſaac, although in him the ſéede were called, nor to Iacob although of hym came the twelue Trybes, not to Moyſes, nor Elyas, nor Aaron, not to anye Prieſte, not to anye Iudge, not to any Prophete, but to the Lorde
<pb facs="tcp:8123:30"/>God of Iſrael onely: But we haue for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken Salomo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and folowed the Sama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritans, we haue not builded one te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Lord, but many temples to Idols.</p>
            <p>As y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Iewes in old time built vp high places in euery citie, and erected altars in euery high hill, &amp; euery nation made themſelfe a God, and put them in the highe places whiche the Samaritanes had made: euen ſo did we, where was there any then that buylded vnto the God of Iſrael? They buylded Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, they erected Altars, they carued I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mages, they appoynted certaine feaſts, they waſhed themſelues at their entrie into the churche, they fell down before their Gods, they kindled lights and bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Frankenſence, ſeuerall Gods had ſeuerall Prieſtes, and was it not ſo in poperie? Might not we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>playne with Ieremie, accordyng to the number of thy cities was thy Gods O I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>huda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and accordyng to the number of the ſtreates, haſte thou erected Altars of confuſion to ſacrifice to Baal. And was not this true in poperie? In euery
<pb facs="tcp:8123:30"/>great Town how many Temples? and till of late not one dedicated to Chriſte. Whereas the virgin Mary had euerye day hir Maſſe, &amp; many Sainctes manye Maſſes: then was Chriſte onelye on the Fryday, (&amp; that but in Cathedrall chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches only) remembred. That which was true while he liued on earth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> birdes of the aire haue neſtes, the foxes dens: that may much more truly be ſpoken of ſuch ſeruices as were done to hym here on earth. Euery where hath Peter a chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, Mary, Paule, Dunſton, Aldate, Gyles, George, Scythe and Katherine, but the ſonne of Man hath not where to hyde his head. <hi>Tertul. li.</hi> 1. <hi>contra Marcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,</hi> ſaid truly, <hi>Inuenio plane ignotis Dijs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras prostitutas, ſed attica idololatria eſt, item incertis Dijs, ſed Romana ſuperſtitio eſt.</hi> I find Altars erected to vnknowen Gods, but it is the Idolarye of Athens, and to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certayne Gods, but it is the ſuperſtition of Rome. Auſtin feared not to ſaye, that there were temples builded to them on earth, whoſe ſoules laye buryed in Hell. Wel might therfore y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> prophetical Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite
<pb facs="tcp:8123:31"/>in Ieremy complaine, and wel may we, that the people haue channged the true God, and ſought for that that pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not: that they haue forſaken the fountaine of the water of life, and haue digged themſelues ceſterues that can hold no water, nay (as Dauid ſaith) their Idolles are multiplyed, after the whiche they make ſo great haſte: Superſtition hathe no hoe, nothing too hotte, nothing too heauy. The Iewes offred their owne children to Moloch. The prieſts of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al did cut and launce themſelues. The people to make a Calfe and an Ephad offered all their richeſt iewells.</p>
            <p>Againe, theſe Iews build not to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they build not houſes, &amp; call them after their own names. They dydde not with the Agregentines build as though they woulde liue for euer, and liue as though they woulde dye for euer, but they builded as men by theyr liues de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous to ſet vp y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of the true God, They to builde Gods houſe ſpared no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but we to builde our owne neſtes plucke from Gods houſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:31"/>
            <p>If <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> Ioſue, &amp; the reſt of the chiefe fathers were not more carefull, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> feet be, both learning, with out which we are like brute beaſts, and religion without which we nothing dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer from Infidels, would ſpéedily periſh.</p>
            <p>I feare me there are that wiſh as he did of the Romains, that they had al but one heade, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might cut off al at once: ſo that wiſh that many Churches were but one church, that it might at once be ouerturned. But will you liue alone vpon the earth? what profiteth it a man to win the whole worlde, if hee looſe hys own ſoule? <hi>Quid proſunt ista cùm caro da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur vermibus anima daemonibus?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt thing is the warrant, <hi>as King Cyrus king of Perſia hath commau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded vs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The warrant wherby the work we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forward, was not of <hi>Zorobabel, althogh</hi> he wer their guide homward, nor of Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dras, although he were a learned ſcribe, and was to reforme both their religion and maners: nor of Nehemias, although he was to finiſh the walls and to deliuer them from oppreſſion.
<pb facs="tcp:8123:32"/>It was not at the commaundement of any Patriarche, of any Prophet, not by the direction of any Prieſte, but of King Cyrus King of Perſia. God, by whome Kyngs do raigne, and that hath not gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſword for nought, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hathe promiſed to raiſe them vp as nurſing fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and nurſing mothers to hys chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che, doth her<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſtir vp Cyrus to further his own cauſe, to ſet forwarde ſhe buyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of his houſe.</p>
            <p>It is worthe the marking. God doth not this worke by anye that were (as it may ſéeme) of hys owne couenante, hee doth not fetch either Saul from kéeping of Aſſes, or Dauid fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> kéeping Shéepe, or Elizeus from the plowe, or Amos fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hearde. But as the deliueraunce is altogither miraculous, ſo is the meanes ordinary, by a Kyng, by K. Cyrus king of Perſia. It is wonderful to ſée y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Gods people in reedifying the holy Te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple did ſo willingly obey a K. in al other points vnholy. But God that would at the firſt frame them to obedience, and in them teach vs and al poſteritie, what we owe
<pb facs="tcp:8123:32"/>to the Lords annoynted, doth here war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant his own worke both by the letters patents of the King of Perſia, and doth alſo by thys hys example ſhewe to the true ſéede of Abraham all his, that if he in his own Church building, (whereas his might haue had legons of Angelles) would yet vſe as a countenaunce to the worlde, the commandement of king Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus, that they in all their actions ſhould next vnder hym depend on them whome the Lord ſhall ſet ouer them. The fyrſte Temple was not builded by a Prieſte, but by Salomon a King.</p>
            <p>It is not ſayd, we will builde as God hathe commaunded: but <hi>it is the Lords houſe, and wee wyll buylde it as Cyrus Kyng of Perſia hath commaunded.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let euery ſoule ſubmit it ſelf therfore to the higher powers, no doubt Paul ſet it eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of that he had learned at Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliels féete.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Chriſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt. Theophylact. Oecumanius,</hi> gather thereof, that all Prieſts, Monkes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, Euangeliſts, Apoſtles, the Pope himſelfe, (if he haue a ſoule) to be ſubiect
<pb facs="tcp:8123:33"/>to thys precept. Submit your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the King as to y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> moſt excellent, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o theſe that are put in authoritie vnder them.</p>
            <p>Did they obey Cyrus a ſtrange king<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſhall wee diſobey oure annoynted of the Lorde?</p>
            <p>Salomon didde builde the firſte, and Cyrus commaundeth thys, and what hath either Patriarke or Prophet to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Hee that withſtandeth Power, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeth Gods ordinaunce.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ignatius ad Magneſian<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Epistola. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo remanſit inultus, qui ſo contra ſuperdores exculit &amp;c.</hi> None eſcaped vnpuniſhed that ſet himſelfe againſt his ſuperiours.</p>
            <p>Dathan and Abyram reſiſted Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but the earth ſwallowed them vppe aliue. Chore and hys complices that conſpired againſt Aaron, two hundreth and fifty perſons, were conſumed with fire. Abſolon deſiring to ſupplante hys father, was hanged by the heare of the head, &amp; his wicked heart ſhot thoroughe with an arrow. When one broughts Dauid word of Saules death, &amp; brought his crown &amp; bracelet, ſignifying alſo that
<pb facs="tcp:8123:33"/>he ſtoode vpon him to rid him out of hys paines being wounded to deathe, &amp; halfe dead, Dauid not onelye not rewarded him, but cauſed him to be ſlain, fearedſte thou not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lords annointede &amp; when hee might twice haue ſlaine hym, he refuſed ſo much as to touch him.</p>
            <p>To conclude, if y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good be euer oppug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> if the deuil go about craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to vndermine the Lords houſe, if he raiſe vp tormentor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to perſecute, falſe brethren to ſeduce, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to choake the good ſéed of Gods word, if he come wyth theſe flattering Samarita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. &amp; ſay, <hi>Let vs build &amp;c.</hi> let vs w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Doues ſimplicitie ioyne the Serpents wiſedome, reſiſt him ſtrong in faith, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municate not with his vnfruitful works, a little of his leauen will leauen our whole lump.</p>
            <p>Let vs conſecrate our ſelues, our bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies &amp; ſoules to ſerue y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord our God: as children obey our father, as brethren loue one another, as me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers defend our head, &amp; as good branches maintaine the roote. Let vs accompte all <hi>vt ſtercora,</hi> as duſte, to winne Chriſt. Better to bee
<pb facs="tcp:8123:34"/>a dore kéeper in the Lordes houſe, than to dwell in the tentes of the wicked.</p>
            <p>Let vs giue moſte humble thankes to God for Zorobabel: let vs liue in faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full obedience in all thynges as to the Lorde: lette vs with Tertulian praye to God to bleſſe Zorobabel with long life, with a faithfull Senate of Elders, with a quiet realme, with a happy peace, wyth an obedient people: Thys God graunte, to whom with his ſome and the holy ghoſt be al praiſe and glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>IMPRINTED AT</hi> London, by Henry <hi>Bynneman.</hi> Anno. <hi>1578.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:8123:34"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
